WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Mentalist
/'men-t3-list/ noun
Someone who uses mental
acuity,hypnosis and/or suggestion.
A master manipulator of
thoughts and behavior.
Are you ready?
Feeling awake, mentally alert? Yes.
Fantastic. Okay.
I want you to imagine a
screen between you and i.
On that screen I wt you
to project a basic shape
Like a square, but not a square.
Got it? Okay.
Lock it in.
Now I want you to
project another shape
And put that shape around
the shape you already have.
Okay.
Excellent.
Here's the fun part.
Now concentrate and project
that onto the back of my mind.
Look right here.
Open up your mind
And send it to me.
Okay, now I'm starting to feel it.
It's a triangle inside a circle.
No. It's not?
No. I was thinking of an
octagon inside a rectangle.
Liar.
All right. All right, you got me.
Hmm, pretty good, huh? He got
me and rigsby the same way.
How did you do that?
Oh, that's nothing.
That's just a calibration
key to real mind reading.
Now I have access to all your
innermost thoughts. Yeah, right.
I'm serious. Okay. So what
am I thinking right now?
You're thinking, "i'm so
glad jane is joking around
And he can't actually read my mind."
No. Well-- well,
actually, yes,
But--but not for
the reason you think.
What reason do I think?
Never you mind.
You're blushing.
You are blushing. Hey, we're up.
Suspected arson/murder
on a farm in marquesa.
The county d.A.'s asking if
we'll check it out. Let's go.
All right.
Chief piller, why the fire truck?
Shouldn't they be gone by now?
Well, took forever
to put the fire out.
There wasn't enough water pressure
To fill the hoses on
account of the drought.
Rich garcia used to have
the best corn in the county.
Now look at it.
Anyway, this is
where we found him--
What was left of him.
There's hardly anything left
for susan and madeleine to bury.
Tough to bury a comrade, I think.
Probably saved your
life more than once.
Vice versa?
How did you know we served together?
You've been crying.
You don't strike me
as the kind of man
That would cry for no reason.
And that's a national
guard signet ring
You're wearing, isn't it?
Yeah, we were in the 3-192 armor.
We did two tours in anbar together.
So you must be the arson specialist.
Uh, no. The
arson specialist--
That would be agent rigsby.
Mr. Jane is a consultant. Mm.
So you--you'll be able to
tell, then, definitively,
Whether the fire was, uh,
arson or accident or whatever?
Two years with the san diego
county arson squad, chief.
I'll be able to tell. Chief
piller, you and your men
Haven't contaminated
the scene, correct?
My men? Uh, it's just me
and terry o'brien, agent.
But yeah, we did like you said.
After we hauled rich out,
we haven't set foot in.
So to determine if it's
arson, I'm gonna need
To analyze the burn path,
find the point of origin,
Check for signs of an accelerant.
It's arson, all right...
And murder.
How can you tell?
This is part of the garage door.
Yes?
The lock's on the outside.
Someone locked garcia
in, lit the place up.
Your friend was murdered.
I'm sorry.
Don't they usually like to
watch their work--arsonists?
Yeah, even more so when
it's coupled with murder.
Maybe this guy's different.
What do you think... Jane?
Jane?
Patrick jane?
Over here!
He watched from up here.
He was here.
What does it look like?
It's sophisticated work.
Electronic timers, mercury switches.
Need the lab on it to be sure,
But looks like they used
a distinctive accelerant--
Rocket fuel, something like
tha so we have a pro at work,
Or a very gifted amateur. Great
And get a cast of the
tire tracks down the road.
You guys go into town
and talk to the guy
Garcia was going to meet that
night--chief, what's his name?
Mitchell reese. He
works the gas station
On main street. Mitchell
reese. On our way
Let's you and me go in and
talk to the widow. Jane?
These folks are from
The california bureau
of investigation.
They're gonna help find
who did this to Rich.
Hi. Nice to meet you.
Thank you for coming.
I, uh... Are you hungry?
There's more than enough.
Oh, i-i could do with a bite.
No, but thank you, mrs. Garcia.
Guess not.
I, uh, put in some
K.P. With the dishes,
And brought in the
firewood, so you're all set.
Thank you. You need anything?
No, ben, I'm good. Thank you so much.
These are the state police people.
Oh, hey. Ben machado.
Anything you need, just
say the word. You got it.
Ben's our, uh, go-to
guy in marquesa.
He just means I'm the only
real estate agent around here
Who takes his commission
in fertilizer and chickens.
You were in the 192nd
as well? That's right.
You have that military bearing.
Rich and ben and me
and a couple other guys
Ran a platoon together.
Yeah. You guys are
gonna catch the bastard
Who did this a-sap, right?
We're certainly gonna try.
I guess that'll have to do.
I'll see you in the morning?
I should go, too.
Ma'am, mind if we ask
you some questions?
No, of course not. Please.
You must be madeleine. Maddy.
Whatever you're selling--pass.
Funny. What are you, a
moron? My dad just died.
Yes. My condolences.
It happens.
You'll learn to live with it.
Not for, uh, a while,
but in the end, you will.
Who are you?
My name's patrick jane. I'm
the man that will find out
Who it was that killed your father
And have him or her--or
them-- put in a prison cell
If you'll talk to me.
If I'll talk to you?
Like I know who did it.
Well, you could help me find out.
Yeah? Your dad was
in the national guard
For a long time.
How come there's no pictures
of him with his buddies?
He used to have all his military crap
In a glass case
on the photo wall--
You know, medals and
pictures and stuff.
But he took it down. Why is that?
How should I know? He
didn't like talking about
What he did over there-- not to me,
anyway. Who did he talk to, your mom?
No. What do you mean by, " no"?
Nothing. I mean, he doesn't
like talking about that stuff.
Why are you so angry at your mom?
I'm...
I'm not.
If you weren't angry,
you'd be with her right now.
She needs you. Her husband just died.
Oh, I'm sure she'll
learn to live with it.
I was watching tv.
Maddy was in her room.
Richard called to say
he was leaving mitch's,
He'd be home soon.
He was doing stuff
for the avocado parade.
And then next thing,
I heard a strange noise,
And I saw
A light out that window.
It was the garage burning,
And rich inside it...
Screaming.
That's what
the noise was--
Rich screaming,
Trying to get out of the garage.
Hello, mrs. Garcia.
Um, I brought corn
chips-- uh, cool ranch.
Thank you, sweetie.
Um, would you like some food?
Oh, could I have some chicken?
Of course, anything
you want. Help yourself
Um, tommy does odd jobs around town.
Challenged, but ever so
independent, bless him.
"challenged"?
He's retarded, mom.
Why can't you ever tell
the truth about anything?
Everything's a lie!
Sorry. You know teenagers.
You know why she's so angry?
She suspects that your lover
Is responsible for the
killing of her father.
My lover?
How dare you?
The policeman. Chief piller?
Him. Maddy suspects no such thing.
Well, that wasn't very convincing.
You want to try that again
with a little more feeling?
You just cannot come in her
And make wild accusations like this.
You never looked him in the eye once.
He kept trying to take your
hand. You wouldn't let him.
The air was practically buzzing
with furtive shame and yearning,
Which tells me that you were lovers
And suggests two
possibilities--
You and piller killed
your husband together,
And now you're remorseful... No.
No.
I believe you.
You'd have found a more
humane method of killing him.
Second possibility-- you
have a horrible feeling
That maybe piller did this thing
To clear the field for himself.
No. Trey would never.
They were best friends.
A best friend that has an affair
With his "best friend's" wife?
Susan...
We'll find out the truth.
When rich came back from the war...
He closed me out.
He went somewhere else.
He wasn't my husband anymore.
Did you have an affair
with trey piller?
Yes.
But trey would never hurt rich.
I know that.
Well, you hope.
Come on, help us out, mr. Reese.
You might have been the last
person to see rich garcia alive.
How about that
What's the problem?
Electrics shot, I bet.
Always the same with the
early '70s models, huh?
Yeah. I gotta get the old pig
runnin' smooth for the parade.
That's what rich and I were
talking about the night he died.
Did you notice anyone else around,
Anyone waiting nearby for him?
What time did he leave?
It was kind of late.
Around 10:00, maybe.
Are you thinkin' this is murder?
Someone cooked him deliberate?
Yes, looks like.
That's weird. Why weird?
Another man killed by arson in the
same town from the same guard unit?
That's weird. Hang on. Another man?
Didn't chief piller tell you?
Three years ago. A guy
called david martin.
Burnt to a crisp. And he
was with the 192nd as well?
Yep. That's what I heard,
anyhow. It was before my time.
Only been in town a year.
David martin lived
up at alton's grove.
Surprised chief piller
didn't mention him.
Van pelt.
This is trey piller's house. Fire
department's on its way, boss.
Is chief piller still
inside? I don't know.
Help!
Stop! Rigsby, wait! Idiot!
Rigsby!
Oh, my god!
Don't move. Don't move.
You'll be all right.
You're gonna be okay.
I'm just gonna lift your arm, okay?
The doctor said we have
to change the dressing
Pretty often at first.
How's chief piller?
The burn unit in sacramento
says it's touch and go.
Hey. Check out dr. Van pelt.
Here. It's that mango crap you like.
How are you feeling? Took
some kick-ass painkillers, man.
I guess this lets piller
out as a suspect, huh?
Yeah, especially since the
doctors at the burn unit
Found date rape drugs in his system.
He told them that he woke up
With smoke and fire all around him.
Interesting new level of cruelty--
Dosing someone so they wake
up just in time to burn alive.
Hey, it's the mummy. So
the fire at piller's house--
Same m.O. As the one
that killed rich garcia.
Accelerant's ethyl
ether. That's a signature.
Tricky stuff to work with,
too. Takes skill, finesse.
Why don't you go and
see what susan garcia
Has to say about all this?
And let's you and me check out
This alton's grove place
where david martin died.
Oh, "the mummy." I get it. Bandages.
And no more painkillers for him.
Why didn't you tell us about
dave martin? What about him?
Same national guard
unit, same death by fire.
That's a pretty spooky coincidence.
But dave's death was an accident,
And nearly three years ago, besides.
An accident? Passed out
with a cigarette, poor fool.
Burned his place
right down to a cinder.
There wasn't a thing left of him.
We had to bury ashes.
Are there any, um...
Are there any other connections
Between this dave
martin and your husband?
Dave was kind of in
business with them--
With rich and trey and ben.
What kind of business? Mar verde real
estate corporation, they called it.
It started out as just a way to
get dave martin a place to live.
"no man left behind"
and all, even dave.
He had problems? He was
an ornery drunk, basically.
Didn't get along with
anyone but his guard buddies.
They got together and
bought a 5-acre piece of land
From the town up at alton's grove.
And after he died, what
happened to the land
Oh, it took forever to get
the land back into their names.
Legal silliness.
I told rich, "don't waste your time.
Land's worth nothing anyhow."
Tommy odds lives up there
now, kind of a caretaker.
And as of now, ben machado's
the only partner still standing.
I guess that's right.
Interesting.
Give me a call after
you speak to machado.
We have an audience.
Hey, tommy.
Remember teresa lisbon?
Um, come in.
So , Tommy...
We are here because...
Mrs. Garcia told my colleague
That you look after this place
for the owners? I keep an eye out.
That's what mr. Garcia said--
"keep an eye out, tommy."
Is that david martin?
Dave was nice.
He didn't make fun
of me, not one time.
You don't smoke
cigarettes, do you? No.
Oh, good. Dave did, and he
got burned up on accident.
Did you see it?
No, I was at the hospital,
'cause my appendix busted.
You want to see my scar?
No. No, but I'm sure
mr. Jane would love to.
Jane?
All this green in the middle of
a drought? Not at alton's grove.
Do you like it? I got
geraniums, too. It's very pretty.
But don't tell, okay?
The--the company
will make me move out.
I won't have nowhere to live.
It seems like it's
coming from the ground.
It's an aquifer-- new
source of groundwater
Must be worth millions.
Worth killing for.
Van pelt?
Yes?
"grace"...
It's a lovely name.
Graceful.
I've been wanting to say
something to you for ages now.
I think now's a good time,
'cause I nearly died.
I love you, grace. I
totally love you. Wh--
You okay?
Yes.
Why did you make that noise?
It's not that I don't like you.
I do.
It's just... We work together,
And there are rules.
And if we were to get together,
One of us would have
to leave the unit,
And I'm junior agent,
so that would be me.
And this job is so important
to me, and I just...
Hey. You want to go to work,
Or you want to play
nurse for king tut?
Work. Definitely work.
Mr. Machado?
Hello?
Maybe he's around back.
Let's check out the barn.
I guess we found machado.
Yeah. Mr. Machado! Ben machado!
Come any closer, and I'll shoot you,
And I will shoot to kill!
Mr. Machado, we're police!
This is the police!
Let me see a badge!
I'm showing the badge. Don't shoot!
Damn!
Okay. Don't shoot!
Turn around.
I didn't know you guys were cops.
What, you thought we were
selling magazine subscriptions?
Hey, check
this out--
The accelerant used in the fires.
Six jugs of it in the barn.
Ethyl ether.
Burns at 600 degrees fahrenheit.
You know what temp
human skin burns at?
250.
I was lucky.
Second-degree burns mostly.
Trey piller's face, it just came off.
Look, I don't know where
that stuff came from.
Someone's framing me.
Somebody frame you for
shooting at us, mr. Machado?
'cause from where I stood,
sure looked like you.
That was a misunderstanding.
I didn't know who you guys were
I was defending myself.
Really? From whom?
From someone trying to kill
me, just like they killed rich
And tried to kill trey.
And why would you be next
on someone's to-burn list
Because we were all
in business together.
And with them gone,
you're the sole proprieto
Of alton's grove--sole
owner of all that
Water. Oh, yeah, ben, we
know about the aquifer-
All that money right under your feet.
But see, that's the perfect motive
For you to burn up piller and
garcia. You. I didn't do it, okay?
Mm-hmm. So you're saying
whoever did fry them
Is going to try to kill you. Now
who is that again? I don't know.
Ben, I gotta say, I'm skeptical.
Why would anyone want
to see you three dead?
Who benefits from that?
Do you want to know my guess?
No.
Dave martin.
Dave martin is dead.
Is he? Did you see his
body, ben, after the fire?
No, but he's dead. You seem pretty
sure about that, like you were there.
What are you insinuating?
Nothing. Nothing at all.
I'm saying you three
tried to kill him
To get alton's grove for yourselves.
That's a lie.
Dave came to you all excited.
He found a liquid fortune...
On property that you bought
for him--practically your land.
Dave owed you. But he didn't
even offer you a taste, did he?
Ungrateful bastard.
That's ridiculous.
We had no idea what
was there till recently.
You and rich and trey
wanted what dave had,
So you set fire to his house,
and you left him there to die.
Imagine-- imagine
the betrayal he felt,
The helpless rage.
That fire was a tragic accident,
and you have no proof otherwise.
Well, someone out there
doesn't need proof.
Someone out there
needs revenge--
Someone very smart
and very determined.
That's why he's terrified
and shooting at cops.
Well, you should be terrified.
I hope you burn like a candle,
you miserable son of a bitch.
You can't talk to me
like that. I have rights.
Yes, you do.
Well, let this creep go. We
don't have anything on him.
Two notes here-- we
already have plenty on him.
One--armed assault
on cho and van pelt,
And two, a barn full of
fire accelerant as well.
The assault was self-defense,
and the accelerant was a plant.
Only two? Actually,
no. Where do you get off
Giving orders in the first place?
I say who goes and
who stays, not you.
Well, that's, uh, fiery
but calm. Very good
Why don't you try it with a
more forceful hand gesture,
Like, "i say who goes
and who stays, not you"?
I'm serious.
So am i. If he's in here, how
is the killer gonna get to him?
He could be the killer,
and even if he's not,
We don't want the killer
to get him. Yes, we do.
Machado is our bait.
He's our tethered goat.
And too bad if the bait gets killed?
Well, yes. That's why you use goats
And not babies or virgins, for
that matter. Machado's not a goat.
Well, you're right.
He's not actually a goat.
He's goatish. He deserves
to suffer a little.
Nobody deserves murder.
Machado helped burn dave
martin alive out of greed.
Jane, we're officers of the law.
You are. I don't care about the law.
I care about justice,
And justice says machado
deserves to suffer.
That's not justice. It's vengeance
What's the difference? What do you
want us to do with machado, boss?
Let him go. Really? Like,
let him go, let him go?
Really, like that.
Okay.
Trying some reverse psychology?
You talk tough.
Maybe it's time you learn
that there's consequences.
If machado gets hurt, it's on you.
Fine with me.
We've never discussed this,
Because I thought it
went without saying,
But when I catch red john,
I'm gonna cut him open
and watch him die slowly,
Like he did with my wife and child.
And if you have a problem
with that, we should talk.
Then let's talk, because
when we catch red john,
We are gonna take him into custody,
And he's gonna be tried in a court
of law. Not if I'm still breathing.
If you try and do violence to him,
I will try and stop you.
If you succeed in doing violence to
him, I will arrest you. I understand.
I hope so.
Well, I'm glad we talked.
I had no idea
You were so bourgeois and
conventional on the issue. Mm.
You thinking what I'm thinking?
No.
How do you know you're not?
I was thinking how I wish
I could go back in time and have sex
With my eighth grade history
teacher miss huffaker.
Is that what you were thinking? No.
I was thinking mitch
reese, the gas station guy
Whatever lights your fire, man.
As a suspect. Think about it.
Who first told us about
dave martin? Mitch reese.
Knew all about it, even though
he'd only been here a year. So?
So they never found
dave martin's body,
And now someone is taking revenge
On the people that murdered
him. Mitch reese is dave martin?
The beard, the burn
scars on his arms,
His whole vibe.
Huh. Wait, dave martin was bald.
Wig. I would put money on
it. Let's go talk to him.
We gotta keep an eye on machado.
To protect machado from the killer,
And if reese is our guy,
that's what we're doing.
Okay, but I'm calling it in.
Mr. Reese, when exactly
did you come to marquesa?
18 months ago, give or take.
And what was it brought you here?
Why marquesa? This place was for sale.
No other reason?
You didn't know anyone in town before
you moved here? Nope. Fresh start.
How did you get those
burn scars on your arms?
Engine blew up on me
while I was working on it.
Why do you ask? Just curious.
Is that your own hair?
Excuse me? On your head. Is that
yours, or are you wearing a wig?
No, it's my own hair. What kind of
a question is that? Mind if we check?
Yes, I do--ow!
Sorry, sir.
Damn. Thanks for your time.
Hello, ben. Aah!
You're gonna need a firin' pin.
You stay back or I will light you up.
Who are you? What do you want?
You know who I am. I have
no freakin' idea, man.
Sure you do, ben.
You tried to kill me.
What?
No. That's impossible.
No, it's not. It's me.
Dave?
Dave martin?
Help! Help!
Help!
No one can hear you, man.
You're gonna die alone,
screaming in agony,
Like I did.
This can't be happening. Help!
Why did you kill me,
ben? We were friends.
You wanted money so bad?
You should've told me.
I would've helped you.
I did tell you.
All of us, we begged you,
but you wouldn't listen,
You selfish bastard!
We didn't want to kill you!
I'm sorry, okay?
I'm sorry!
See how much better that feels?
I forgive you. Can't speak
for dave martin, though.
You son of a bitch.
You don't want to make
things worse for yourself.
Rigsby! Cho!
What?
I killed an intruder in my barn.
How was I to know it was a cop?
If that's even what you
are. What are you exactly?
Rigsby! Cho! They're right outside.
Oh, are they?
Wait a second. One
thing you're forgetting.
Machado!
Ben machado!
That's not...
You ready to die?
What the hell's going on?
Oh, dear.
Rigsby! Cho!
Jane, you in there?
Oh, crap. Jane!
Jane!
Jane! Are you ok?
That was close.
Where were you guys? We
called in to check out a lead.
Yeah, lisbon didn't know
you were about to pull
An idiotic stunt. Sorry.
No hard feelings. Whoa,
whoa. Oh, arrest this man
He confessed to killing
dave martin. Cool.
Got it all here. Turn around. Again.
Yeah, yeah, you could...
Yeah, I'll just...
I'll just wait here.
Freeze!
That's good. Got him.
Hello, sir.
Tommy, what were you doing at
the machado house last night?
Sir, do you got any soda?
What kind do you want?
My super favorite is root beer.
Okay, I'll get you some in a minute.
Do you like root beer? No.
Do you like to burn things, tommy?
No.
No? You sure about that?
Am I sure about what?
What were you doing
at the machado house?
Watching the barn burn down.
You liked watching it, huh?
Gave you a nice feeling?
No, I was scared. I don't
like fire. Fire hurts.
Do you have root beer?
It doesn't make sense. All
the evidence says it's him.
There was ethyl ether
traces all over him.
But the arsonist used
an electronic timer
And rocket fuel, and tommy's
wearing velcro sneakers.
Call him challenged,
retarded, whatever you want--
There's no way he's capable of this.
What if he had a
partner? Maybe that's it.
Somebody's manipulating
him. Someone he trusts.
Give me a moment with him.
Do you mind? Sure thing.
Don't make a mess.
Cop humor.
Not funny.
I'm supposed to be finding
out who put you up to this.
You see, my friends
think you're an idiot.
Everybody says that.
Sometimes they're not nice.
Yes.
Being a fool gives you a
sort of power, doesn't it?
You're there, and you're not there.
It's like having a wizard's
cloak of invisibility.
I don't understand
what you're saying, sir,
But I like wizards.
The--the other man said
he'd get me a root beer,
But he never did. Revenge
is a hard road, isn't it?
It's like when captain
ahab was chasing moby-dick.
The whale died all right, but
the "peapod" went down, too.
"pequod." ahab's
ship is the "pequod."
Exactly.
The "pequod."
Silly of me.
Here's your copy here.
I must say, I'm impressed.
I know english literature professors
That haven't read "moby-dick."
I like whales. They eat squids.
Looking back, I should
have known it was you
The first time I saw you.
Only an idiot would
wear a t-shirt like that
To a house in mourning...
An idiot or a daring killer
with a warped sense of humor.
You're going down for this one.
You might as well go
down as your real self.
You have pulled off
something amazing.
You should be proud in a way.
That root beer coming?
Why don't you just
talk to me, thomas?
There's no point in hiding anymore.
I can see you.
What do you want to know?
Hello.
Good to meet you.
I am curious. Are there two of you,
Or is tommy just an
act that you put on?
Oh, please. I'm not a mental case.
Tommy's an act... A-a performance.
That you never turn off.
He amuses me.
He protects me.
When I was 18, I jacked a car
And got caught.
But when I pulled the tommy
act, the cops let me go.
I've gotten much better
since then, of course.
Good enough to avenge
dave martin's death.
Three months ago, the
company finally got
A permit to exploit the aquifer.
All that money.
I put things together,
Realized what they'd done to dave.
Thanks.
I confess, i-i never really
could get to the end of it.
Ahab does die, doesn't he? Yes.
But so does the whale. That's my
point. Revenge doesn't come cheap.
Oh, spare me your moralizing.
I know what revenge costs.
It's worth the price.
David martin had
many flaws, no doubt.
But he was my friend. My friend.
Those animals, they
deserve what they got.
It was justice.
You admit to killing rich garcia
and trying to kill trey piller?
I watched them scream
and writhe in agony...
And it was beautiful.
It was redemptive.
You wouldn't understand.
Agent cho does the formal
police charging stuff.
We're done.
Good luck, thomas.
Would you do one thing for me?
You can ask.
Would you tell maddy garcia...
I'm sorry for hurting her?
Sorry? He's sorry?
You tell him if he
ever gets out of jail,
I'm gonna set him on fire and
see how he likes it. Maddy.
I am! Your
father wasn't--
And don't you talk about him.
You have no right! No right!
Your father killed a man
And tommy killed him out
of revenge. You know that.
Revenge is a poison.
Revenge is for fools and for madmen.
I don't care.
Yes, you do.
Hey, come here. Come on.
We have to go, but, uh,
could you do me a favor?
Could you both do me
a favor? Would you hug?
Just pretend like
you love each other.
Please? That's it.
Just like that. That's good.
Now hold that pose until we leave.
It'll help lisbon and me
Feel like we've actually
made a difference. Thank you.
So?
Seems like this whole thing
Changed your mind
about vengeance. Huh?
"revenge is for fools and madmen."
That was rather good, I thought.
Total nonsense, but
quite good nonetheless.
Shall we?